Records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society
1878-1916
1888-1902
Bridgeport Scientific Society
BHC-MSS 0006
6 lft. 4.5 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
The records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society represent an overview of the activities of the first tenants of the Barnum Institute of Science and History, today housing the Barnum Museum. It contains administrative information in the form of society minutes, documentation of collection acquisitions, and extensive documentation of the lectures hosted by the group.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Collection was likely transferred from the Bridgeport Scientific Society when it ceased to function in the 1930s. No deed of gift has been located.
Biography
The building that now houses the Barnum Museum originally was constructed for the sake of the Bridgeport Scientific Society, Bridgeport Medical Society, and the Fairfield County Historical Society. It was completed in 1893, having been constructed by the firm of Longstaff and Hurd. Longstaff and Hurd also constructed P.T. Barnum's last home, "Marina". Both organizations existed before the building was built, with the Fairfield County Historical Society being founded in 1881 and the Bridgeport Scientific Society being founded in the year 1878. The Scientific and Historical societies, along with the Bridgeport Medical Society, made use of the building until 1933. During that time, they collected a number of items that survive in the collection of the current Barnum Museum. They hosted lectures from a number of scientific and technological luminaries and provided a place for the public to be educated. Eventually, the societies collapsed, as membership dues and subscriptions were not enough to pay for upkeep. At that time they ceded ownership of the building and the collections to the City of Bridgeport.
Scope and Content of Collection
The contents of the Records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society primarily offer an overview of the day to day function of the society. This is due to the heavy presence of meeting minutes and correspondence, and the fact that there is much less information regarding the specimen collections or research sponsored by the society. However, the extensive amount of lecture programs offer insight into the educational outreach the society conducted and what members believed would capture public attention to bring in attendees to these events. This information is contained in series VI, which runs from 1881-1907 with very few gaps. It is complimented by the scrapbooks in series VIII which contain newspaper clippings that offer summaries of the events.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the Records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society is primarily chronological and is broken into the following series. Series I- minutes and executive documents This series begins with a summary of the history of the society and Barnum building for researchers to use. Minutes and laws are given priority, and then reports are listed based on officer rank. Additional material based on rank is listed, followed by reports.
Series II- correspondence Correspondece with various individuals.
Series III- financial documents Bills are arranged chronologically, membership information is arranged by lifecycle. Bills relate to building maintenance and to other expenses. The membership portion is placed in financial documents due to the presence of subscription lists and due books. This material is arranged by lifecycle of membership from application to resignation.
Series IV- curatorial documentation The material present represents information on the collection practices of the society. Bound manuscript material containing records of donations is prioritized, followed by other manuscript material, then print material.
Series V- general activity Material represents a small amount of paper that could not be fit into other series and is arranged chronologically.
Series VI- lectures and programs These printed materials represent the general outreach and education the society engaged in. The lecture programs reveal a season's worth of speakers and the annual address is given by the president of the society. As the material begins in 1881 it also demonstrates the pre-Barnum building era. Arranged chronologically.
Series VII- record books Arranged chronologically, these record books contain member lists, meeting summaries and minutes.
Series VIII- scrapbooks. Arranged chronologically these scrapbooks contain clippings about the lecture programs.
The record books and scrapbooks are oversized, and due to their delicate nature, cannot be housed in manuscript boxes with the rest of the collection.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Barnum, P.T. (Phineas Taylor), 1810-1891; Secor, David Pell, 1824-1909; Barnum Institute of Science and History; Barnum Museum; Bridgeport Scientific Society; Fairfield County Historical Society; Historical Societies; Natural History Museums; Scientific Societies
Related Collections
The Barnum Museum holds a small collection of documents similar to the materials present in this collection. That collection, Records of the Barnum Institute of Science and History (BM MSS 0001) contains additional documentation related to separate entities that were the Bridgeport Scientific Society and the Fairfield County Historical Society prior to their move into the Barnum building. Also present in that collection is more extensive documentation of the opening day exercises of the building itself, biographical information of the personnel in the building and most importantly, a catalog of material housed on site.
- Series I, Minutes and executive documents
  - History of the Bridgeport Scientific Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive committee meetings, correspondence, and reports, 1881-1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General meeting minutes of the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1882-1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - By-laws, articles association, and charter of Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1878-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charter, Rules, and Bylaws of the Bridgeport Scientific and Historical Society, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Additional resolutions and notes, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer’s reports, 1880-1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Secretary’s reports, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Presidency acceptance, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vice president decline, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report of the Joint Committee for the Division of Space in the Barnum Institute, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II, Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1877-1916 (Box 1, Folder 12-26)
- Series III, Financial documents
  - Bills, 1877-1892 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Membership applications, 1880-1899 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Membership lists, 1887-1892 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subscription lists, 1882-1888 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Due books, 1880-1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Membership resignations, 1878-1905 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
- Series IV, Curatorial documentation
  - Records of donations to the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1890-1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Record of print donations to the Bridgeport Scientific and Historical Society, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Curator and librarian reports and correspondence, 1880-1892 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Appeal for help of Bridgeport citizens to be involved with donating to collection, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series V, General activity
  - Invitation to Dedication of Barnum Institute Building, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reports of science projects sponsored by society, 1882-1892 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Observatory plans, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Additional material, 1893-1897 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Seal of Fairfield County Historical Society, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series VI, Lectures and programs
  - Lecture program, 1881-1882 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual address before the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lecture program, 1882-1883 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual address before the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lecture program, 1883-1884 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual address before the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lecture program, 1884-1886 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Annual address before the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lecture program, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Annual address before the Bridgeport Scientific Society, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Science and the spiritual, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lecture program, 1887-1888 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Science applied to economic questions, lecture by Charles M. Du Puy, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lecture program, 1890-1892 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - List of birds found in the vicinity of Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lecture program, 1892-1898 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Lecture ticket, 1898-1899 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Lecture program, 1899-1900 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Historical exercises for the Bridgeport centennial, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lecture program, 1901-1907 (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
  - Programs for lectures, bound together, 1881-1882 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence about arranging lectures, 1880-1900 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Printed material advertising lectures and topics, 1880-1910 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Series VII, Record books
  - Record book for 1877-1886, pre-Barnum building. Includes constitution, member list, and meeting summaries (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Record book for 1877-1906, pre- and Barnum building era. Member list only. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Record book for 1899-1916, Barnum building era. Includes meeting summaries, and budgets, both handwritten and typed-then-pasted-in. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Record book for Executive Committee, record of meetings, pre- and Barnum building era. Includes meeting minutes, both handwritten and typed-then-pasted-in, 1881-1899 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series VIII, Scrapbooks
  - Clippings scrapbook, clippings focus on the lectures and include summaries of them., 1887-1897 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)